<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin/>
        <origin/>
        <origin/>
        <pubdate>20140701</pubdate>
        <title>United States National Atlas Airports, 2010-2012</title>
        <edition>2014</edition>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Data and Maps for ArcGIS®</sername>
          <issue>2014 - World, Europe, and United States</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace/>
          <publish>Environmental Systems Research Institute (Redlands, Calif.)</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Location: \usa\trans</othercit>
        <onlink>http://purl.stanford.edu/db614zf6817</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin/>
            <pubdate>20140701</pubdate>
            <title>ESRI Data and Maps 2014</title>
            <edition>14</edition>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace/>
              <publish>Environmental Systems Research Institute (Redlands, Calif.)</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This point shapefile represents airports in the United States, Puerto Rico, and U.S. Virgin Islands with airport passenger enplanements of 25 passengers or more per year. This layer is part of the 2014 ESRI Data and Maps collection for ArcGIS 10.2.</abstract>
      <purpose>U.S. National Atlas Airports provides information about the locations, names, location identifiers, and enplanements of airports for conducting geographic analysis on national and large regional scales.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20100101</begdate>
          <enddate>20121231</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-176.646047</westbc>
        <eastbc>-64.801720</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.285448</northbc>
        <southbc>17.701559</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>lcsh</themekt>
        <themekey>Airports</themekey>
        <themekey>Airport control towers</themekey>
        <themekey>Runways (Aeronautics)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>transportation</themekey>
        <themekey>location</themekey>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>geonames</placekt>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>United States Virgin Islands</placekey>
        <placekey>Puerto Rico</placekey>
      </place>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>None</tempkt>
        <tempkey>2010-2012</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>The data are provided by multiple, third party data vendors under license to Esri for inclusion on Data &amp; Maps for ArcGIS® for use with Esri® software. Each data vendor has its own data licensing policies and may grant varying redistribution rights to end users. Please consult the redistribution rights below for this data set provided on Data &amp; Maps. As used herein, “Geodata” shall mean any digital data set consisting of geographic data coordinates and associated attributes. 

The redistribution rights for this data set: Public domain data from U.S. government is freely redistributable with proper metadata and source attribution. 

The terms and conditions below apply to all the data sets provided on Data &amp; Maps. 

Proprietary Rights and Copyright: Licensee acknowledges that the Data and Related Materials contain proprietary and confidential property of Esri and its licensor(s). The Data and Related Materials are owned by Esri and its licensor(s) and are protected by United States copyright laws and applicable international copyright treaties and/or conventions. 

Limited Warranty and Disclaimer: Esri warrants that the media upon which the Data and Related Materials are provided will be free from defects in materials and workmanship under normal use and service for a period of ninety (90) days from the date of receipt. 

THE DATA AND RELATED MATERIALS ARE EXCLUDED FROM THE LIMITED WARRANTY, AND THE LICENSEE EXPRESSLY ACKNOWLEDGES THAT THE DATA CONTAINS SOME NONCONFORMITIES, DEFECTS, OR ERRORS. ESRI DOES NOT WARRANT THAT THE DATA WILL MEET LICENSEE'S NEEDS OR EXPECTATIONS; THAT THE USE OF THE DATA WILL BE UNINTERRUPTED; OR THAT ALL NONCONFORMITIES, DEFECTS, OR ERRORS CAN OR WILL BE CORRECTED. ESRI IS NOT INVITING RELIANCE ON THIS DATA, AND THE LICENSEE SHOULD ALWAYS VERIFY ACTUAL DATA. 

EXCEPT FOR THE LIMITED WARRANTY SET FORTH ABOVE, THE DATA AND RELATED MATERIALS CONTAINED THEREIN ARE PROVIDED "AS-IS," WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. 

HIGH RISK ACTIVITIES: 
(A) THE DATA AND RELATED MATERIALS ARE NOT FAULT-TOLERANT AND ARE NOT DESIGNED, MANUFACTURED, OR INTENDED FOR USE OR RESALE FOR INSURANCE UNDERWRITING OR WITH CRITICAL HEALTH AND SAFETY OR ONLINE CONTROL EQUIPMENT IN HAZARDOUS ENVIRONMENTS THAT REQUIRE FAIL-SAFE PERFORMANCE, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE OPERATION OF NUCLEAR FACILITIES, NAVIGATION OR GUIDANCE (I.E., AIRCRAFT, NAUTICAL VEHICLE, ETC.), OR COMMUNICATION SYSTEMS, AIR TRAFFIC CONTROL, EMERGENCY RESPONSE, TERRORISM PREVENTION OR RESPONSE, LIFE SUPPORT, OR WEAPONS SYSTEMS ("HIGH RISK ACTIVITIES"). ESRI SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTY OF FITNESS FOR HIGH RISK ACTIVITIES. 

(B) TO THE EXTENT PERMITTED BY LAW, LICENSEE AGREES TO INDEMNIFY, DEFEND, AND HOLD ESRI, ITS OFFICERS, DIRECTORS, EMPLOYEES, AGENTS, SUBCONTRACTORS, LICENSORS, SUCCESSORS, AND ASSIGNS HARMLESS FROM AND AGAINST ANY AND ALL LIABILITY, LOSSES, CLAIMS, EXPENSES (INCLUDING ATTORNEYS' FEES), DEMANDS, OR DAMAGES OF ANY KIND, INCLUDING DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, PUNITIVE, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, ARISING OUT OF OR IN ANY WAY CONNECTED WITH LICENSEE'S USE OR PERMITTING THE USE BY OTHERS OF THE DATA, AND VENDOR'S HARDWARE OR SOFTWARE FOR HIGH RISK ACTIVITIES. DELIVERY OF THE DATA, AND VENDOR'S HARDWARE OR SOFTWARE DOES NOT CONSTITUTE A WAIVER OF THE RIGHTS AND OBLIGATIONS SET FORTH IN THIS ARTICLE. 

Exclusive Remedy and Limitation of Liability: The entire liability of Esri or its licensor(s) and Licensee's exclusive remedy shall be to terminate the Agreement upon Licensee returning the Data and Related Materials to Esri with a copy of Licensee's invoice/receipt and Esri returning the license fees paid to Licensee. 

IN NO EVENT SHALL ESRI AND/OR ITS LICENSOR(S) BE LIABLE FOR COSTS OF PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOST PROFITS, LOST SALES, OR BUSINESS EXPENDITURES, INVESTMENTS, OR COMMITMENTS IN CONNECTION WITH ANY BUSINESS; LOSS OF ANY GOODWILL; OR FOR ANY INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF THIS AGREEMENT OR USE OF THE DATA AND RELATED MATERIALS, HOWEVER CAUSED, ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, AND WHETHER OR NOT ESRI OR ITS LICENSOR(S) HAVE BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE. THESE LIMITATIONS SHALL APPLY NOTWITHSTANDING ANY FAILURE OF ESSENTIAL PURPOSE OF ANY EXCLUSIVE REMEDY. 

Third Party Beneficiary: Esri's licensor(s) has (have) authorized Esri to (sub)distribute and (sub)license its (their) data as incorporated into the Data and Related Materials. As an intended third party beneficiary to this Agreement, the Esri licensor(s) is (are) entitled to directly enforce, in its own name, the rights and obligations undertaken by the Licensee and to seek all legal and equitable remedies as are afforded to Esri. 

In the event that the data vendor(s) has (have) granted the end user permission to redistribute the Geodata, please use proper proprietary or copyright attribution for the various data vendor(s), and provide the associated metadata file(s) with the Geodata. In compliance with FGDC metadata standards, Esri has attempted to practice proper metadata methodologies by providing any data source information, descriptions, and file names to assist in this effort.
</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Esri</cntorg>
          <cntper>ArcGIS Content Team</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>380 New York Street</address>
          <city>Redlands</city>
          <state>California</state>
          <postal>92373-8100</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>909-793-2853</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>909-793-5953</cntfax>
        <cntemail>info@esri.com</cntemail>
        <hours>8:00 a.m.–5:00 p.m. Pacific time, Monday–Friday</hours>
        <cntinst>In the United States– Please direct all inquiries regarding software/data pricing and consulting services to your local Esri Regional Office. For support, you may contact Esri Support Center by telephone (voice) between 5:00 a.m. and 5:00 p.m. Pacific time, Monday through Friday, by dialing 888-377-4575; facsimile (fax) available at 909-792-0960; electronic mail (e-mail) support@esri.com; or visit http://support.esri.com/; Esri holidays excluded. 

Outside the United States– Please direct all inquiries regarding software/data pricing, sales, support, and consulting services to your local Esri Office. This information can be found at http://www.esri.com/about-esri/offices. For other questions or comments, you may contact Esri headquarters by e-mail, telephone, or fax or write to us.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>National Atlas of the United States, ESRI and U.S. Geological Survey. (2014). United States National Atlas Airports, 2010-2012. ESRI.</datacred>
    <native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2.3552</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>The shapefile is converted to file geodatabase (FGDB) format using tools in ArcGIS. The geometry is checked, and if needed repaired.</logic>
    <complete>After processing, the data set is checked for drawing display and number of records and file sizes compared with source materials.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The horizontal positional accuracy is unknown.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin/>
            <pubdate>20120701</pubdate>
            <title>1:1,000,000-Scale Airports of the United States</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace/>
              <publish>National Atlas of the United States</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>The data were derived from an extract of the Public-Use Airports database of the National Transportation Atlas Databases-2010 (NTAD-2010), published by the Bureau of Transportation Statistics, Department of Transportation.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.nationalatlas.gov/</onlink>
            <onlink>http://www.nationalatlas.gov/atlasftp.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>1000000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <mdattim>
              <sngdate>
                <caldate>20100101</caldate>
              </sngdate>
              <sngdate>
                <caldate>20120701</caldate>
              </sngdate>
            </mdattim>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>National Atlas</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Attribute and geospatial data</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The following steps were performed by Esri: Downloaded airprtx010g.shp (Airports - July 2012) from the National Atlas of the United States®. Projected the dataset into WGS 1984. Renamed the field AIRPT_NAME to NAME. Converted the values in the fields NAME, CITY, and COUNTY to title case. Converted the data set to SDC. Created ArcGIS® layer file (.lyr), projection file (.prj), and spatial indices.</procdesc>
        <srcused>National Atlas</srcused>
        <procdate>20130422</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Converted the dataset into a file geodatabase.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20140401</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>940</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>airports</enttypl>
        <enttypd>The points represent locations where aircraft can take off and land, usually equipped with associated buildings and facilities, and used primarily by conventional, fixed-wing aircraft.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Atlas of the United States and the United States Geological Survey</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ICAO</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The 4-character International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) airport location indicator.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Air Carrier Activity Information System (ACAIS)</codesetn>
            <codesets>U.S. Department of Transportation, Federal Aviation Administration</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>IATA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The 3- or 4-character International Air Transport Association (IATA) airport location code.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE)</codesetn>
            <codesets>UN/LOCODE Code List 2011-1</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The name or identification for the airport.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Geographic Names Information System</codesetn>
            <codesets>U.S. Board on Geographic Names</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CITY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The name of the city where the airport is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Names for the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The 2-character abbreviation for the state in which the airport is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Department of Commerce, National Institute of Standards and Technology</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Federal Information Processing Standards 5-2</codesetn>
            <codesets>National Institute of Standards and Technology</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATE_FIPS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The FIPS code (two-digit number) for the state in which the airport is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Department of Commerce, National Institute of Standards and Technology</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Federal Information Processing Standards 5-2</codesetn>
            <codesets>National Institute of Standards and Technology</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>COUNTY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The name of the county or county equivalent in which the airport is located. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Federal Information Processing Standards 6-4</codesetn>
            <codesets>National Institute of Standards and Technology</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FIPS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The 5-digit FIPS code of the county or county equivalent in which the airport is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Federal Information Processing Standards 6-4</codesetn>
            <codesets>National Institute of Standards and Technology</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_ENP</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The total enplanements during calendar year 2008. Total enplanements are the sum of large certified, commuter, air taxi, foreign, and in-transit enplanements.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>0</edomv>
            <edomvds>National Atlas of the United States</edomvds>
            <edomvd>The number of total enplanements is unknown. This value applies to Air Force bases only.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Numbers for the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ELEV</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The elevation, in feet, at the highest point on the centerline of the usable landing surface. The value is measured to the nearest foot with respect to mean sea level.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Numbers for the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CNTL_TWR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>An indication of whether the airport includes a control tower.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Atlas of the United States</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvds>National Atlas of the United States</edomvds>
            <edomvd>A control tower is present.</edomvd>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>No control tower is present.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>National Atlas of the United States</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Stanford Geospatial Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>Branner Earth Sciences Library</address>
          <address>Mitchell Building, 2nd Floor</address>
          <address>397 Panama Mall</address>
          <city>Stanford</city>
          <state>California</state>
          <postal>94305</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-723-2746</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>brannerlibrary@stanford.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>See access and use constraints information.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150424</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Esri</cntorg>
          <cntper>ArcGIS Content Team</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>380 New York Street</address>
          <city>Redlands</city>
          <state>California</state>
          <postal>92373-8100</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>909-793-2853</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>909-793-5953</cntfax>
        <cntemail>info@esri.com</cntemail>
        <hours>8:00 a.m.–5:00 p.m. Pacific time, Monday–Friday</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
